Guide to the Edward K. Barsky Photograph Collection ALBA.PHOTO.125
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Edward K. Barsky Photographs
circa 1937
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Barsky, Edward K., 1895-1975
ALBA.PHOTO.125
2.5 Linear Feet (5 boxes)
Dr. Edward K. Barsky (1897-1975) was a prominent physician who led a group of American medical volunteers in Spain during the Civil War. The images in this collection were either taken by Barsky and his assistant or accrued in the course of his work as a surgeon in Spain. The collection contains portraits of Dr. Barsky, Albert Einstein and Jolliet Curie, Francisco Franco and Benito Mussolini, American Medical Bureau to Aid Spanish Democracy (AMB) doctors and nurses, Canadian nurses affiliated with the MacKenzie-Papineau Battalion, and Spanish doctors and nurses. The collection also contains snapshots of surgeries, medical vehicles, political demonstrations/rallies, Spanish civilians, and scenes of Spanish village life.
(5 document boxes) Approximately 450 black and white photographs sized from 1.75 x 2.25 inches to 8 x 10 inches, and approximately 335 negatives sized from 1.25 x 1.25 inches to 2.5 x 5 inches.
Provenance
The Edward K. Barsky Papers were donated to the Abraham Lincoln Brigade Archives by Vita Barsky in the late 1970s. The collection came to New York University in January 2001 as part of the original acquisition of Abraham Lincoln Brigade Archives collections, formerly housed at Brandeis University. The images in the Barsky Photographic collection were separated from the Barsky manuscript material at the time of processing.
Access Restrictions
Materials are open to researchers. Please contact the Tamiment Library & Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives for more information and to schedule an appointment, tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu or 212-998-2630.
Historical/Biographical Note
Dr. Edward K. Barsky was a prominent surgeon who led a group of American medical volunteers during the Spanish Civil War. For further biographical information on Edward Barsky, and to review the scope and contents of his manuscript collection see,
The Guide to the Edward K. Barsky Papers, ALBA 125.
The images in this collection were either taken by Barsky and his assistant or accrued in the course of his work as a surgeon in Spain.
Scope and Content Note
The Dr. Edward Barksy Photograph Collection includes approximately 450 black and white photographs ranging in size from 1 ¾ x 2 ¼ inches to 8 x 10 inches. The approximately 335 negatives range in size from 1 ½ x 1¼ inches to 2 ½ x 5 inches. The negatives are stored separately from the prints, in Box 4 and 5.
Series I: Prints
The approximately 450 black and white prints are arranged alphabetically by topic and most are photographs taken in Spain during the Civil War. Approximately half of the prints relate to the practice of medicine including portraits of doctors and nurses and recovering patients. The series contains portraits of Dr. Barsky, Albert Einstein and Jolliet Curie, Francisco Franco and Benito Mussolini, American Medical Bureau to Aid Spanish Democracy (AMB) doctors and nurses, Canadian nurses affiliated with the MacKenzie-Papineau Battalion, and Spanish doctors and nurses. The collection also contains snapshots of surgeries, AMB ambulances and other medical vehicles, political demonstrations/rallies, bombed/shelled buildings, Spanish civilians, a Spanish campesino shaking the hand of a Mexican campesino, scenes of Spanish village life, and unidentified group photographs. Some of the prints of are credited to: Foto Mayo [Madrid?]; Libsohn-Ehrenberg, New York, New York; General Photographic Co., Inc. New York, New York; and Walter Rosenblum. The photographs taken outside of Spain include portraits of Dr. Barsky for Spanish Refugee Appeal, portraits of Joilot-Curie and Einstein at Princeton, New Jersey and photographs of the mercy ship SS Mexique. The SS Mexique carried Spanish refugees from Spain to Mexico.
Series II: Matched Negatives
There are approximately 170 negatives that match prints in Series I. They are arranged alphabetically by topic.
Series III: Unmatched Negatives
The approximately 170 negatives that do not match any prints are arranged alphabetically by topic. The negatives include portraits of Dr. Barsky, surgeries, medical vehicles, political demonstrations/rallies, Spanish civilians, and scenes of Spanish village life.
Arrangement
Folders arranged alphabetically by topic in the prints and negatives series.
The photographic prints are identified by four numbers separated by colons. The first number refers to the collection number, the second to the box number, the third to the folder number, and the fourth to the individual print. For example, the first print in this collection is labeled 125:1:1:1. Negatives are numbered in the same fashion and if there is a matching print, the print number is listed below the negative number.
The files are grouped into 3 series:
Missing Title
I: Prints
II: Matched Negatives
III: Unmatched Negatives
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Barsky Manuscript Collection, ALBA 125
Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Participation, American.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Pictorial works.; Spain |x History |y Civil War, 1936-1939 |v Portraits.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Hospitals.; Black-and-white photographs.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939.; Negatives (photographic); Spain. Ejercito Popular de la Republica. Abraham Lincoln Battalion; Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade; Barsky, Edward K., 1895-1975; Libsohn-Ehrenberg.; Rosenblum, Walter, 1919-2006; Spain. Ejercito Popular de la Republica. Brigada Internacional, XV; Franco, Francisco, 1892-1975; Joliot-Curie, Irène, 1897-1956; Mussolini, Benito, 1883-1945; Einstein, Albert, 1879-1955.; Medical Bureau to Aid Spanish Democracy; Medical Bureau and North American Committee to Aid Spanish Democracy; North American Committee to Aid Spanish Democracy
- Series I: Photographs
  - American Medical Bureau (AMB): Ambulance, ca.1937 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - AMB: Doctors, ca.1937 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - AMB: Nurses, ca.1937 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - At the Front: Non-Combat, ca.1937 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Barricades, ca.1937 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Barsky, Edward: Portraits, ca.1937 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Barsky, Edward: Spanish Refugee Appeal, ca.1937 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Behind the Lines: Daily Life of the Soldiers, ca.1937 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Behind the Lines: Rest and Relaxation, ca.1937 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Bombed/Shelled Buildings, ca.1937 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Casualties, ca.1937 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Demonstrations: In Spain, ca.1937 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Einstein, Albert and Irène Joliot-Curie: Portrait at Princeton, New Jersey, ca.1937 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Franco, Francisco General and Mussolini, Benito, ca.1937 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Galeani, Umberto, ca.1937 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Group Portraits: Identified, ca.1937 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Group Portraits: Unidentified, ca.1937 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - International Red Cross: Ambulance, ca.1937 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - MacKenzie Papineau Battalion: Ambulance, ca.1937 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - MacKenzie Papineau Battalion: Nurses, ca.1937 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Medical: Ambulances, ca.1937 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Medical: Doctors and Nurses, ca.1937 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Medical: Hospital, ca.1937 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Medical: Injured/Recovering Patients, ca.1937 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Medical: Surgery, ca.1937 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Mercy Ships: SS Mexique, ca.1937 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Monuments/Statues, ca.1937 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Portraits: Individuals, unidentified, ca.1937 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Spanish Cities, ca.1937 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Spanish Civilians, ca.1937 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Spanish Civilians: Campesinos/Peasants, ca.1937 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Spanish Civilians: Children, ca.1937 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Spanish Civilians: Refugees, ca.1937 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Spanish Civilians: Relaxing/Playing Croquet, ca.1937 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Spanish Civilians: Workers, ca.1937 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Spanish Civilians: Workers, Laundry Women, ca.1937 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Spanish Civilians: Workers, Seamstresses, ca.1937 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Spanish Countryside, ca.1937 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Spanish Villages: Daily Life, ca.1937 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Spanish Villages: Street Scenes, ca.1937 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Stone, Al, ca.1937 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Taroncon, ca.1937 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Valla Paz, ca.1937 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Vanzant, Frances Dr.: Portrait, ca.1937 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Vehicles, ca.1937 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Vehicles: Locomotive, ca.1937 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Vehicles: Transport, ca.1937 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Waters, George Walter, ca.1937 (Box 3, Folder 19)
- Series II: Matched Negatives
  - AMB: Ambulance, ca.1937 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - AMB: Nurses, ca.1937 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Barsky, Edward Dr, ca.1937 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Behind the Lines: Daily Life of the Soldiers, ca.1937 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Behind the Lines: Rest and Relaxation, ca.1937 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Group Portraits: Unidentified, ca.1937 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - International Red Cross: Ambulance, ca.1937 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Medical: Ambulance, ca.1937 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Medical: Doctors and Nurses, ca.1937 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Medical: Hospital, ca.1937 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Medical: Injured/Recovering Patients, ca.1937 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Medical: Surgery, ca.1937 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Monuments/Statues, ca.1937 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Spanish Cities, ca.1937 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Spanish Civilians, ca.1937 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Spanish Civilians: Children, ca.1937 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Spanish Civilians: Relaxing/Playing Croquet, ca.1937 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Spanish Civilians: Workers, Laundry Women, ca.1937 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Spanish Civilians: Workers, Seamstresses, ca.1937 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Spanish Countryside, ca.1937 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Spanish Villages: Daily Life, ca.1937 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Spanish Villages: Street Scenes, ca.1937 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Vehicles, ca.1937 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Vehicles: Transport, ca.1937 (Box 4, Folder 24)
- Series III: Unmatched Negatives
  - AMB: Ambulance, ca.1937 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - AMB: Doctors, ca.1937 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - AMB: Nurses, ca.1937 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Barsky, Edward Dr., ca.1937 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Behind the Lines: Daily Tasks, ca.1937 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Behind the Lines: Rest and Relaxation, ca.1937 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Bombed/Shelled Buildings, ca.1937 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Fortifications, ca.1937 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Groups: Unidentified, ca.1937 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Individuals: Unidentified, ca.1937 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - International Red Cross: Ambulance, ca.1937 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Medical: Hospital, ca.1937 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Medical: Injured/Recovering Patients, ca.1937 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Medical: Nurses, ca.1937 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Medical Surgery, ca.1937 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Rallies/Demonstrations, ca.1937 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Spanish Civilians, ca.1937 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Spanish Civilians: Children, ca.1937 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Spanish Civilians: Relaxing/Playing Croquet, ca.1937 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Spanish Civilians: Workers, Laundry Women, ca.1937 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Spanish Civilians: Workers, Seamstresses, ca.1937 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Spanish Countryside, ca.1937 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Spanish Villages: Daily Life, ca.1937 (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Spanish Villages: Panormas/Street Scenes, ca.1937 (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Unidentified/Unknown: Over/Under-Exposed Negatives, ca.1937 (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Vehicles, ca.1937 (Box 5, Folder 26)